Guide to the Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Photographs, 1888-1944; Series VIII; 1.75; (4 boxes)
  - FUTURIST PHOTOGRAPHS
    - 399. Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni). Il Perfetto Borghese (camuffamento d'oggetti ), 1930. Title in- scribed on verso. Signed in pencil on verso. [See: Sotheby's catalogue, Italian Futurist Photographs, 1982, n. 59, and See: Giovanni Lista, Futurismo e Fotografia, 1979, p. 220, and See: Giovanni Lista, Photographie Futuriste Italienne 1911-1939, 1982, n. 121.] (Box 52, Folder 1966)
    - 400. Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni). Spirit portrait of the Futurist Mario Carli, 1930. Signed on verso. [See: Sotheby's catalogue, Italian Futurist Photographs, 1982, n. 65, and See: Giovanni Lista, Futurismo e Fotografia, 1979, p. 104, and See: Giovanni Lista, Photographie Futuriste Italienne 1911-1939, 1982, n. 126.] (Box 52, Folder 1966)
    - 401. Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni). Pastore con somarello [Shepherd with Donkey], 1930. Signed on verso. [See: Sotheby's catalogue, Italian Futurist Photographs, 1982, n. 60, and See: Giovanni Lista, Futurismo e Fotografia, 1979, p. 218, and See: Giovanni Lista, Photographie Futuriste Italienne 1911-1939, 1982, n. 122.] (Box 52, Folder 1966)
    - 402. Photographer unknown. Photomontage. FTM speaking. Inscribed on verso: "fotodinamico." (Box 52, Folder 1966)
    - 403. Photographer unknown. Photomontage. FTM and the Futurist group of Macerata. Photo processed by S. Accorroni, Macerata. Dated 1933 by Giovanni Lista in Futurismo e fotografia (1979). (Box 52, Folder 1966)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS OF WORKS OF ART
    - 404. Acquaviva. Aeroritratto Marinetti (painting). Postcard. (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 405. Duplicate of n. 404. (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 406. Balla, Giacomo (or his daughter). Portrait of Jannelli (painting). Inscribed on verso: "ricambia a Paolo Buzzi cordialissimi auguri per il nuovo anno gennaio 1942." (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 407. Boccioni, Umberto. Development of a Bottle in Space (sculpture). 1912. Collection Museu de Arte Contemporanea da Universidade de Sao Paulo. Typescript of museum cataloguing information on verso. (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 408. Boccioni, Umberto. A Futurist Soirée (drawing). Left to right: Boccioni, Pratella, FTM, Carra and Russolo. (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 409. Caviglioni, Angelo. Ostacolista (painting). Postcard. (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 410. Crali, Tullio. Prima che si apra il paracadute (painting). Exhibited in the XXII Esposizione Inter- nazionale d'Arte, Venice. Postcard. (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 411. Duplicate of n. 411. (?) (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 412. Depero, Fortunato. Portrait of FTM (painting). (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 413. Forlin, Corrado. Il Duce (sculpture). 23 April 1937. Inscribed on verso: " Il Duce Potero metterlo in una posa pui virile, vero? [illegible] Corrado Forlin del gruppo Savoie 23 A[pri]le XV." (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 414. Gutnayer, J. (architect). Drawing of a house. Inscribed and signed on recto and verso. Stamped on verso. (Box 52, Folder 1967)
    - 415. Marinetti, F.T. Bataille à 9 étages du Mont Altissimo (parole in libertà ). 1915. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 416. Menin, M. Portrait of FTM (painting)., 1941. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 417. Pancera, G.?. Portrait of Paolo Buzzi (sculpture). 1952-53. Inscribed on verso. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 418. Papazof. (painting). Inscribed on verso: "Papazof." (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 419. Plinio, Verossi. L'Aviazione (painting), 1942?. Exhibited at the XXIII Esposizione Internazionale d'Arte de Venezia. Inscribed on verso: "Scalone S. Bartolomeo 1, Verona." (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 420. Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni). Il Lavoro (painting). Formerly in the collection of the Confederazione fascista lavoro e industria. Inscribed in blue pencil on verso. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 421. Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni). L'Assalto (painting), ("fantasia decorativa per l'alcova dell'ardito Mario Carli") [decorative fantasy for the bedroom of the "ardito" Mario Carli.] Postcard made for the Esposizione Internazionale di Venezia, 1926, by the Movimento Futurista Italiano. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 422. Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni). La Festa dei Gagliardetti (painting), ("Fantasia futurfascista"). Postcard published by the Movimento Futurista Italiano. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 423. Duplicate of n. 424. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 424. Tosato, F. and de Giorgio. Architectural ren- dering of a hotel. Signed by di Giorgio on recto. Inscribed by de Giorgio on verso: "Con l'ing. Tosato sono capo gruppo degli urbanisti Padovani tutti passatisti che si stanno convincendo. I piu devoti saluti, de Giorgio." Postcard. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 425. Artist unknown. FTM's profile superimposed on an aerial view (painting). Postcard. (Box 52, Folder 1968)
  - OTHER POSTCARDS AND PHOTOS/WITHOUT FTM OR FUTURISTS
    - 426. Gulf of Catania. Crowd of sailors and civilians. Inscribed on verso: "Gazeta de Mo." (Box 52, Folder 1968)
    - 427. Pietrasanto (Tuscany). Unident- ified people on the beach at this bathing resort on the Ligurian sea. Postcard. [Removed from Marinetti M977C.], n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1969)
    - 428. Maramures, Rumania. Chapel. Inscribed on verso: "Chapelle en bois en Maramures.", n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1969)
    - 429. Mt. Etna. Postcard., n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1969)
    - 430. Mt. Etna. Postcard., n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1969)
    - 431. Postcard. Ship at sea., n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1969)
    - 432. Postcard. Libya, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1969)
- Clippings, 1914-1983; Series IX; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Articles from periodicals that refer to Futurism
    See: Oversize, Box 54, folder 2011
    Includes: 1. Fortunato Bellonzi, "Vitalità del futurismo," Via dell'Impero [?]
    2. Vittorio Orazi, "Nuovi avviamenti della poesia italiana e loro cause," Via dell'Impero [?]
    3. Corrado Govoni, "Marinetti, poète," La Phalange (Paris), année 10, n. 17, 15 April 1937.
    4. Col. Basseggio, "L'adunata di Piazza S. Sepolcro," periodical unknown
    5. Jean Brzekowski, "Le Futurisme italien en Pologne," periodical unknown
  - Pages clipped from Latinité (Paris), année 3, n. 9, Sept. 1931 (with pencil markings, by FTM?) (Box 53, Folder 1970)
    - 1. pp. 12-20 from Gonzague Truc, "Entretiens d'outre-tombe; Platon ou des idées."
    - 2. pp. 51-66 from Prax, "Haïti."
  - Issues (some not complete) of non-Italian newspapers with articles, photos, and/or cartoons that refer to Futurism:
    See: Oversize Box 55, folder 2012
    - 1. Hobl (Russian), 1914
    - 2. Ultra (Spanish), 1920
    - 3. Prager Presse (Prague), 1923 Jan 7
    - 4. Prager Presse (Prague), 1923 Jan 14
    - 5. Prazsky Illustrovany Zpravodaj, 1923
    - 6. Facla (Bucharest), 1930
    - 7. Tribune 1935 (Brussels) (2 copies)
    - 8. El Español (Spanish), 1945
  - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals that refer to World War I, (13 items)
    See: Oversize Box 55, folder 2013
  - Clippings from newspapers that refer to the death of F.T. Marinetti, (14 items) (Box 53, Folder 1971)
  - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals, (57 items)
    See: Oversize Box 56, folder 2014
  - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals, 1909-30; (18 items)
    See: Oversize Box 56, folder 2015
  - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals, 1931-83; (23 items)
    See: Oversize Box 56, folder 2016
- Special Files, 1918-1940; Series X; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Futurist stationery, (26 sheets) (Box 53, Folder 1972)
  - FTM's address books (3) and loose sheets with hand- written addresses (Box 53, Folder 1973)
  - Calling cards, (5 items) (Box 53, Folder 1974)
  - Proof-sheets for a Futurist exhibition catalogue with manuscript corrections (Box 53, Folder 1975)
  - Publishers' prospectuses Includes: BCM, Astra e il Sottomarino BCM, Viaggio di Gararà FTM, Spagna Veloce and Toro Futurista FTM, Il Poema Africano della Divisione '28 Ottobre' FTM, L'Aeropoema del Golfo della Spezia FTM, O Oriente [with photograph of FTM] FTM, La Ville Charnelle and Les Dieux S'en Vont - D'Annunzio Reste FTM, Mondadori editions of various works
    See: Oversize Box 56, folder 2017
  - Publicity broadsides Includes: "La vittoria dei Futuristi" (for Poesia "Schiaffi, Pugni e Quadri Futuristi" (for Il Futurismo ) "Paolo Buzzi glorificato nella battaglia di Roma e nel Banchetto ai futuristi" and "Il poeta futurista Luciano Folgore" by Arturo Calza (for I Poeti Futuristi
    See: Oversize Box 56, folder 2018
  - Carteggio sottoscrittori. March, 1934 List of contributors to a gift of an automobile for FTM on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of Futurism (Box 53, Folder 1976)
  - Theatre box-office receipts and author's royalties accounts., 1921-31 (Box 53, Folder 1977)
  - Contract and other materials concerning FTM's South American lecture tour, 1926. (Box 53, Folder 1978)
  - Itinerary for FTM's visit to Morocco, Nov 1932. (Box 53, Folder 1979)
  - PNF [Fascist Party] membership and convention cards, (4 items) (Box 53, Folder 1980)
  - Istituto Editoriale del Littorio. Roma 1 item stock certificate [?] Signed by Settimelli and Mario Carli
    See: Oversize Box 56, folder 2019
  - Medical prescriptions [?] 2 items (Box 53, Folder 1981)
  - FTM's urine analysis, 1923. 2 items (Box 53, Folder 1982)
  - Partial register of people attending FTM's funeral [?] 6 p. (Box 53, Folder 1983)
  - Manuscript inscriptions to FTM from other authors Includes: Virgil Huzum, 1930; Carlos Ibarguren, 1936; and unidentified, n.d. 4 items (Box 53, Folder 1984)
  - Telegram form. 1928 Mar 22 1 item (Box 53, Folder 1985)
  - Floor plan of Casa Colonica 1 item (Box 53, Folder 1986)
  - Bills, shipping receipts, etc. 1919-42 11 items (Box 53, Folder 1987)
  - Publishers' accounts. 1930, 1935 3 items (Box 53, Folder 1988)
  - Postal order receipts. 1918-32 (Box 53, Folder 1989)
  - Invitation to a lecture on the literary activity of Benedetta, 1936. 1 item (Box 53, Folder 1990)
  - Statuto della Società Anonima Cooperativa 16-page typescript. [signed by D. Stefan?] (Box 53, Folder 1991)
  - Printed items that refer to World War I. 1918, n.d. 6 items (Box 53, Folder 1992)
  - La Fortuna, Giornale dei dilettanti del lotto (Velletri), anno XXVII, n. 311, Feb 1918. 1 item (Box 53, Folder 1993)
  - Sheet music dedicated to FTM and BCM Includes: V. Mortari, "Teatro della Sorpresa" F. Bochen, "Preludio Satirico" Silvio Mix, "Profilo Sintetico-Musicale" 6 items
    See: Oversize Box 56, folder 2020
  - Map of Geneva 1 item (Box 53, Folder 1994)
  - X-rays of FTM's head. Envelope from the Istituto di Radiologia, Rome, 1940. 2 items (Box 53, Folder 1995)
  - Notes by BCM found removed from books catalogued in the Marinetti collection 5 items (Box 53, Folder 1996)
  - Press release from Agencia A.L.A. 1938 Jun 8 (Box 53, Folder 1997)
  - Press release: "La Nuova Direzione del Movimento Futurista Italiana" with typescript carbon list of "Futuristi Volantari per l'Africa Orientale" (printed in La Forza Aug 30 1935) (Box 53, Folder 1998)
    See also: Series IV, folder 1356
- Oversize, 1905-1983; Series XI; 5.5; (3 boxes)
  This series contains oversize items from Series III, IV, V, IX and X.
  - Letters to and about Filippo Tommaso Marinetti
    - Moréas, Jean to FTM (Box 54, Folder 1999)
  - Writings by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti
    - WRITINGS
      - "Ali d'Italia"
        - Printed version, Bordata, 1931 Mar 1 (Box 54, Folder 2000)
      - Ancora una volta 'Guerra sola igiene del mondo'
        - Printed version (as "1926 in Francia: Assemblea di donne"), La Gazzetta del Popolo - Torino 1940 Oct 13 (Box 54, Folder 2000)
      - "Il Battesimo Nero"
        - Printed version, in unidentified newspaper, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 2000)
      - I Diritti artistici, propugnati dai futuristi italiani. Manifesto al governo fascista
        - Printed manifesto, with a note in upper left corner from FTM to an unidentified "Carissimo" asking for his opinion. Notes in pencil, in an unidentified hand on pp. 1-4 (in red pencil on p. 3). 4 p. (Box 54, Folder 2001)
      - "Elogio di Capri"
        - Printed version, Carriere di America, 1928 Mar 11 (Box 54, Folder 2001)
        - Printed version, pamphlet, n.d.
      - Fondation et manifeste du Futurisme
        - Proof. 3 p., numbered 1-2. (Box 54, Folder 2001)
      - "Le fotografia delle radiazioni vitale"
        - Printed version, in unidentified newspaper, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 2001)
      - "Italiani liberatevi dalle abitudini inglesi: manifesto futurista"
        - Printed version, La Forza, 1935 Aug 30 (Box 54, Folder 2001)
      - [Journal]
        - Autograph manuscript notes. 22 p. (Box 54, Folder 2002)
      - "Luci Veloce"
        - Excerpt, printed version, Gazzetta del Popolo, 1929 Jan 4 (Box 54, Folder 2002)
      - "L'Oceano del Cuore"
        - Excerpt, printed version, Brillante, 1927 Dec 21 (Box 54, Folder 2002)
      - "Il Paesaggio nei sentimenti e nelle poesie di Napoli"
        - Printed version, Roma, 1935 Jun 5 (Box 54, Folder 2002)
      - Poema chimico della luce tessuta
        - Autograph manuscript signed on last page. 22 p. (Box 54, Folder 2002)
      - "Poesia Plastica Musica e Architettura Africane"
        - Printed version, La Forza, 1935 Aug 30 (Box 54, Folder 2002)
      - La Radio futurista
        - Printed version (as "Manifeste de la Radia Futuriste"), Comoedia, 1933 Dec 15 (Box 54, Folder 2003)
      - "Simultaneità parolibera nella Divina Commedia"
        - Printed version, Meridiano di Roma, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 2003)
      - Zang Tumb Tumb
        - Page 38 bis of proof of the French version. With corrections, unpublished. (Box 54, Folder 2003)
        - Publicity broadside, titled "Marinetti in Russia" (Box 54, Folder 2003)
  - Writings by Others
    - Buzzi, Paolo
      - "Aeropoesia per Aeropittura", autograph manuscript poem, with underlining in various colors and corr- ections in the same hand. Signed at the bottom of the last page and dated Rome, 2 Jan 1938, "Mostra d'Aeropittura futurista". 5 p. (Box 55, Folder 2004)
      - "Golfo di Napoli", autograph manuscript poem with title, underlining and asterisks in red. Signed on last page and dated Milan 1936. 20 p. (Box 55, Folder 2005)
      - "Stornellata Ditirambica", autograph manuscript poem, with notations and additions in the same hand. Signed at the bottom of the last page and dated Milan, Jul 1937. 11 p. (Box 55, Folder 2006)
    - Di Napoli, Franco
      - "Ossecorp la Noub Osnes", typescript carbon of a play, dedicated to FTM, and signed on the last page. Dedication in manuscript on page [1]. Also a second copy, in proof form, with no corrections, but with "Bragagia" written in FTM's hand on the first page 37 p., numbered [1]-23 and [1]-8. (Box 55, Folder 2007)
    - Marinetti, Benedetta Cappa
      - Le Forze Umane, publicity broadside, titled "Una Nuova Scrittrice Futurista" by Paolo Buzzi, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 2008)
    - Tommasini, Vittorio Osvaldi (Farfa, pseudonym)
      - "Tuberie", autograph manuscript poem, signed at the top of page 1. 6 p., numbered 1-6. (Box 55, Folder 2009)
    - Tunirati, Domenico
      - "Medium", autograph manuscript poem, in Italian, signed. "c. 12" written in blue pencil at top; probably published in Poesia. 1 p. (Box 55, Folder 2010)
  - Clippings
    - Articles from periodicals that refer to Futurism (Box 55, Folder 2011)
    - Issues (some incomplete) of non-Italian newspapers with articles, photos, and/or cartoons that refer to Futurism Includes: (Box 55, Folder 2012)
      - 1. Hobl (Russian), 1914
      - 2. Ultra (Spanish), 1920
      - 3. Prager Presse (Prague), 1923 Jan 7
      - 4. Prager Presse (Prague), 1923 Jan 14
      - 5. Prazsky Illustrovany Zpravodaj, 1923
      - 6. Facla (Bucharest), 1930
      - 7. Tribune 1935 (Brussels) (2 copies)
      - 8. El Español (Spanish), 1945
    - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals that refer to World War I 13 items (Box 55, Folder 2013)
    - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals, (57 items) (Box 56, Folder 2014)
    - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals, 1909-30; (18 items) (Box 56, Folder 2015)
    - Clippings from newspapers and periodicals, 1931-83; (23 items) (Box 56, Folder 2016)
  - Special Files
    - Publishers' prospectuses Includes: BCM, Astra e il Sottomarino BCM, Viaggio di Gararà FTM, Spagna Veloce and Toro Futurista FTM, Il Poema Africano della Divisione '28 Ottobre' FTM, L'Aeropoema del Golfo della Spezia FTM, O Oriente [with photograph of FTM] FTM, La Ville Charnelle and Les Dieux S'en Vont - D'Annunzio Reste FTM, Mondadori editions of various works (Box 56, Folder 2017)
    - Publicity broadsides Includes: "La vittoria dei Futuristi" (for Poesia ) "Schiaffi, Pugni e Quadri Futuristi" (for Il Futurismo ) "Paolo Buzzi glorificato nella battaglia di Roma e nel Banchetto ai futuristi" and "Il poeta futurista Luciano Folgore" by Arturo Calza (for I Poeti Futuristi ) (Box 56, Folder 2018)
    - Istituto Editoriale del Littorio. Roma 1 item stock certificate [?] Signed by Settimelli and Mario Carli (Box 56, Folder 2019)
    - Sheet music dedicated to FTM and BCM Includes: V. Mortari, "Teatro della Sorpresa" F. Bochen, "Preludio Satirico" Silvio Mix, "Profilo Sintetico-Musicale" 6 items (Box 56, Folder 2020)